Guide to the Ida Treat Bergeret Papers, 1889-1978
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Ida Treat Bergeret Papers,
1889-1978
Bergeret, Ida Treat, 1889?-1978
4.3 cubic feet (7 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Papers reflect her personal and professional life and include travel diaries and notes, manuscripts and published versions of her articles and stories on China, Russia, Tahiti, Abyssinia, Djibouti, and the Red Sea slave trade, 1928-1967; correspondence with her two of her three husbands, Paul Vaillant-Couturier and Andre Bergeret; letters from Wolfgang Wolff written from Tahiti, 1934-1939; correspondence with her literary agent Marie Rodell, 1965-1967, and with the New Yorker and other publishers and editors; 86 letters from her friend Pierre Teilhard de Chardin, 1926-1952, and correspondence, contracts, and royalty statements, 1968, pertaining to Chardin's book Letters to Two Friends, 1926-1952; notes, clippings, and scrapbooks concerning her experiences in London during World War II, 1943-1945; manuscripts and publications by other authors; letters and articles of Simone and Max Begonen; and family and personal photographs.
Biographical Note
Ida Treat was born in Joliet, Illinois, in 1899 and attended Western Reserve University. After earning a doctorate in letters at the University of Paris she returned in 1913 to Western Reserve, where she taught romance languages for the next seven years. In the 1920s she went back to France, where she lived as a writer and journalist for more than twenty years. While working as a correspondent for Paris Vu in the 1930s, she traveled throughout Europe, China, and the South Pacific. Her articles and stories appeared in United States periodicals such as The Nation, The New Yorker, Harpers, and The Saturday Evening Post. She was married She was married three times, to Raymond O'Neil, Paul Vaillant-Couturier and André Bergeret. In her writing she used the name Ida Treat.
In 1948 Ida Treat Bergeret came to Vassar as Professor of English. She retired in 1954 after more than five years of teaching writing courses. When she died in 1978, her colleague and friend, Barbara Swain said that "she had freedom and adventure in a way that might make her a choice for a feminist model today. But she wouldn’t like that very much. She was always too independent for playing roles."
Scope and Content Note
Papers reflect her personal and professional life and include travel diaries and notes, manuscripts and published versions of her articles and stories on China, Russia, Tahiti, Abyssinia, Djibouti, and the Red Sea slave trade, 1928-1967; correspondence with her two of her three husbands, Paul Vaillant-Couturier and Andre Bergeret; letters from Wolfgang Wolff written from Tahiti, 1934-1939; correspondence with her literary agent Marie Rodell, 1965-1967, and with the New Yorker and other publishers and editors; 86 letters from her friend Pierre Teilhard de Chardin, 1926-1952, and correspondence, contracts, and royalty statements, 1968, pertaining to Chardin's book Letters to Two Friends, 1926-1952; notes, clippings, and scrapbooks concerning her experiences in London during World War II, 1943-1945; manuscripts and publications by other authors; letters and articles of Simone and Max Begonen; and family and personal photographs.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Begonen, Simone; Begonen, Max; Wolff, Wolfgang; Vaillant-Couturier, Paul, 1892-1937; Bergeret, Andre; Teilhard de Chardin, Pierre; Rodell, Marie; Bergeret family
Organizations:
Vassar College--Faculty; New Yorker
Subjects:
Slavery--Middle East; Women--Diaries; Publishers and publishing; World War, 1939-1945--England--London; Women college teachers; Women travelers; Women authors
Places:
China--Description and travel; Soviet Union--Description and travel; Tahiti--Description and travel; Ethiopia--Description and travel; Djibouti--Description and travel; Middle East--Description and travel; London (England)--Description and travel; Abyssinia--Description and travel
Document Types:
Scrapbooks; Diaries; Photographs
VCL Categories:
Literature and Writing; Slavery and Antislavery; Travel
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke November 2006.
Last updated March 2024.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ida Treat Bergeret.
Anchored Heart manuscript in Box 7 was a gift of the Hot Springs County Library, 2013.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence to Bergeret from de Chardin
- Series II. Correspondence to Bergeret from Paul Vaillant-Couturier
- Series III. Correspondence to Bergeret from Various Individuals
- Series IV. Correspondence to Bergeret from Others
- Series V. Fan Mail
- Series VI. General Correspondence to Bergeret
- Series VII. Correspondence from Bergeret to Various Individuals
- Series VIII. Unpublished Manuscripts by Bergeret
- Series IX. Other Manuscripts by Bergeret
- Series X. Published Manuscripts by Bergeret
- Series XI. Published Articles by Bergeret
- Series XII. Translations and Reviews by Bergeret
- Series XIII. Manuscripts by Others
- Series XIV. Articles by Others
- Series XV. Poetry by Others
- Series XVI. Articles By and About Teilhard de Chardin
- Series XVII. Clippings
- Series XVIII. Financial Papers
- Series IXX. World War II
- Series XX. Printed Material
- Series XXI. Diaries
- Series XXII. Biographical: Ida Treat Bergeret
- Series XXIII. Drawings
- Series XXIV. Photographs and Scrapbooks
Container List
- Series I. Correspondence to Bergeret from Teilhard de Chardin
  - 1926 Apr 26 (Folder 1.1)
  - 1926 May 3-23 (Folder 1.2)
  - 1926 Jun 2-11 (Folder 1.3)
  - 1926 Jun 25 - Jul 19 (Folder 1.4)
  - 1926 Aug 6 - Sep 15 (Folder 1.5)
  - 1926 Oct 12 - Nov 14 (Folder 1.6)
  - 1926 Nov 28 - Dec 25 (Folder 1.7)
  - 1927 Jan 22 - Mar 24 (Folder 1.8)
  - 1927 Apr 6 - May 11 (Folder 1.9)
  - 1927 May 24 - Oct 2 (Folder 1.10)
  - [1927] Nov 30 - [1933] Oct 7 (Folder 1.11)
  - [1933] Oct 20 - 1934 Jun 30 (Folder 1.12)
  - 1934 Aug 18 - 1935 [Paris] (Folder 1.13)
  - 1935 [Paris] - 1935 Sep 18 (Folder 1.14)
  - 1936 Jan 22 (Folder 1.15)
  - 1936 Oct 30 - 1937 Jun 28 (Folder 1.16)
  - 1937 Aug 15 - 1948 Mar 7 (Folder 1.17)
  - 1948 Mar 16 - May 26 (Folder 1.18)
  - 1948 Jul 8 - Dec 3 (Folder 1.19)
  - 1949 Jul 19 - 1950 Jul 25 (Folder 1.20)
  - 1950 Aug 30 - 1952 Oct 14 (Folder 1.21)
  - 1926 Apr 26 - Jun 11, (photocopy) (Folder 1.22)
  - 1926 Jun 25 - Sep 15, (photocopy) (Folder 1.23)
  - 1926 Oct 12 - Dec 25, (photocopy) (Folder 1.24)
  - 1927 Jan 22 - Apr 20, (photocopy) (Folder 1.25)
  - 1927 Jul 4 - Aug 27, (photocopy) (Folder 1.26)
  - 1927 Jul 24 - [1933] Oct 7, (photocopy) (Folder 1.27)
  - [1933] Oct 20 - 1934 Nov 17, (photocopy) (Folder 1.28)
  - 1934 Dec 31 - 1935 Sep 18, (photocopy) (Folder 1.29)
  - 1936 Jan 22 - 1937 Jun 28, (photocopy) (Folder 1.30)
  - 1937 Aug 15 - 1948 Apr 16, (photocopy) (Folder 1.31)
  - 1948 Apr 19 - 1948 Dec 3, (photocopy) (Folder 1.32)
  - 1949 Jul 19 - 1950 Jul 25, (photocopy) (Folder 1.33)
  - 1950 Aug 30 - 1952 Oct 14, (photocopy) (Folder 1.34)
- Series II. Correspondence to Bergeret from Paul Vaillant-Couturier
  - 1921-1924, (9 letters) (Folder 1.35)
  - 1926 Jul 13 - [1927 Nov 9?], (4 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 1.36)
  - 1928 Jan 28 - Oct [19?], (6 letters, 1 fragment) (Folder 1.37)
  - 1929 Feb 26 - Mar 18, (12 TS) (Folder 1.38)
  - 1930 Jun 2, 1934, (3 letters, 2 fragments, 1 telegram) (Folder 1.39)
  - 1934, 1937, (5 letters, 1 telegram) (Folder 1.40)
  - undated, (106 letters, 16 frag., 3 drawings) (Folders 1.41-1.51)
  - undated, (36 TS) (Folders 1.52-1.56)
- Series III. Correspondence to Bergeret from Various Individuals
  - Begouen, Simone and Max, 1951 Sep 9 - 1954 Sep 26 (Folder 1.57)
  - Begouen, Simone and Max, 1954 Jan 15 - 1957 Nov 17 (Folder 1.58)
  - Begouen, Simone and Max, 1958 Feb 2 - 1960 Oct 10 (Folder 1.59)
  - de Cizancourt, Annick, 1966 Apr 2 - 1968 Dec 26 (Folder 1.60)
  - de Cizancourt, Annick, 1969 Feb 9 - 1973 Feb 5 (Folder 1.61)
  - de Cizancourt, Joël, 1965 Jan 24 - Nov 22 (Folder 1.62)
  - de Cizancourt, Joël, 1966 Jan - Dec (Folder 1.63)
  - de Cizancourt, Joël, 1967 Jun 10 - Jul 11 (Folder 1.64)
  - de Cizancourt, Joël, 1968 Feb 15 - Dec 27 (Folder 1.65)
  - de Cizancourt, Joël, 1969 Sep 8 - Dec 21 (Folder 1.66)
  - de Cizancourt, Joël, 1970 [Feb 21?] - Aug 29 (Folder 1.67)
  - de Cizancourt, Joël, 1972 Dec 8 - 1973 Jan 18 (Folder 1.68)
  - Michel, Dr. François, undated (Folder 1.69)
  - Rodell, Marie, 1965 Apr 27 - 1967 Apr 26 (Folder 1.70)
  - Treat, Francis H. [father], 1922 Aug 15 - Dec 19 (Folder 1.71)
  - Treat, Francis H., 1923 Jan 3 - Nov 7 (Folder 1.72)
  - Treat, Francis H., 1924 Jan 8 - Oct 22 (Folder 1.73)
  - Treat, Francis H., 1925 Jun 14 - 1927 Jan 12 (Folder 1.74)
  - Treat, Francis H., 1928 Mar 8 - 1929 May 15 (Folder 1.75)
  - Treat, Grace D. [sister], 1930 Jan 12 - 1970 Aug 27 (Folder 1.76)
  - Treat, Grace D., undated (Folder 1.77)
  - Treat, Dorothy A. [sister], 1963 May 1 (Folder 1.78)
  - Wolff, Wolfgang, 1934 (Folder 4.1)
  - Wolff, Wolfgang, 1935 (Folder 4.2)
  - Wolff, Wolfgang, 1936 (Folder 4.3)
  - Wolff, Wolfgang, 1937-1946 (Folder 1.79)
  - Family members [unidentified], 1969 Dec 26 - 1973 Jan 5 (Folder 1.80)
  - Family members, undated (Folder 1.81)
  - Family members, undated (Folder 1.82)
- Series IV. Correspondence to Bergeret from others
  - A, undated (Folder 1.83)
  - B, undated (Folder 1.84)
  - C – E, undated (Folder 1.85)
  - F, undated (Folders 1.86-1.87)
  - G, undated (Folder 1.88)
  - H – L, undated (Folder 1.89)
  - M, undated (Folder 1.90)
  - N – O, undated (Folder 1.91)
  - P – R, undated (Folder 1.92)
  - S, undated (Folders 1.93-1.95)
  - T – Z, undated (Folder 1.96)
- Series V. Fan Mail
  - 1941 Mar 25 - Nov 10 (Folder 1.97)
  - 1941 Nov 19 - 1942 Feb 24 (Folder 1.98)
  - 1942 Feb 24 - Dec 1 (Folder 1.99)
  - 1948 Mar 29 - 1951 Mar 8 (Folder 1.100)
  - 1954 Mar 12 - 1959 Jan 9 (Folder 1.101)
  - 1959 Apr 4 - Jul 30 (Folder 1.102)
  - 1959 Oct 14 - 1966 Dec 2 (Folder 1.103)
  - undated (Folders 1.104-1.106)
- Series VI. General Correspondence to Bergeret
  - from Publishers, 1948 Mar 29 - 1951 Jun 28 (Folder 6.107)
  - from Publishers, 1953 Feb 2 - 1957 Jan 29 (Folder 1.108)
  - from Publishers, 1941 Jun 5 - 1967 Oct 20 (Folder 1.109)
  - Letters of condolence - death of André Bergeret, undated (Folder 1.110)
  - re: China, undated (Folder 1.111)
  - re: "Bouillon", undated (Folder 1.112)
  - re: André Bergeret and divorce, undated (Folder 1.113)
  - re: André Bergeret and divorce, undated (Folder 1.114)
  - re: New American Library, undated (Folder 1.115)
  - re: New American Library, undated (Folder 1.116)
  - re: Pearls, Arms and Hashish, undated (Folder 1.117)
  - [unidentified], undated (Folder 1.118)
- Series VII. Correspondence from Bergeret to various individuals
  - [Armgard], [no year] Sep 24 (Folder 1.119)
  - Begouen, Simone, undated (Folder 1.120)
  - de Cizancourt, Jöel and Annick, 1966 Mar 12, 1969 Mar 18 (Folder 1.121)
  - Vaillant-Couturier, Paul, undated (Folder 1.122)
  - Vaillant-Couturier, Paul, undated (Folder 1.123)
  - Vaillant-Couturier, Paul, undated (Folder 1.124)
  - Vaillant-Couturier, Paul, undated (Folder 1.125)
  - Vaillant-Couturier, Paul, undated (Folder 1.126)
  - Rodell, Marie, 1965 May 16 - 1967 Jul 28 (Folder 1.127)
  - Vaillant-Couturier, Marie-Claude, 1937 (Folder 1.128)
  - Weil, Elsie, 1936 Dec 30 (Folder 1.129)
  - [unidentified], 1966 Jan 13 (Folder 1.130)
- Series VIII. Unpublished Manuscripts by Bergeret
  - The Apple, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.131)
  - The Artists as Young Men, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.132)
  - Cordon Bleu, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.133)
  - The Enemy, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.134)
  - Master—And Dog, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.135)
  - The Monument, undated; (TS, draft) (Folder 1.136)
  - The Monument, undated; (TS, draft) (Folder 1.137)
  - The Monument, undated; (TS, draft) (Folder 1.138)
  - Dogs of War, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.139)
  - The Occupant, undated; (TS, fragment) (Folder 1.140)
  - A Piece of Research, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.141)
  - Rebuild the City, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.142)
  - The Spanish Neighbor, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.143)
  - untitled manuscript, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.144)
- Series IX. Other Manuscripts by Bergeret
  - Abyssinia - Red Sea – Djibouti, undated (Folders 2.1 - 2.16)
  - Athens in the Morning, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.17)
  - Baby, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.18)
  - Back to Paris, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.19)
  - Bird Story (A Brittany Fable), undated; (MS, fragment) (Folder 2.20)
  - Bouillon, working copy, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.21)
  - Bouillon, working copy, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.22)
  - Brittany – Justice, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.23)
  - Camargue, undated; (MS, fragment) (Folder 2.24)
  - China: Friend in China, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.25)
  - China: Lin Chu-win, a New Chinese Star, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.26)
  - China: My Friend Hsu, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.27)
  - China: My Friend Hsu, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.28)
  - China: My Friend Hsu, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.29)
  - China: My Friend Hsu, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.30)
  - China: My Friend Hsu, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.31)
  - China: Miscellaneous Fragments, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.32)
  - China: Miscellaneous Fragments, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.33)
  - China: Missing Men, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.34)
  - China: Missing Men, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.35)
  - China: Missing Men, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.36)
  - China: Tsiang, undated (Folder 2.37)
  - Early Chapters of a Biography, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.38)
  - Early Chapters of a Biography, pp 1-20, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.39)
  - Early Chapters of a Biography, pp 21-43, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.40)
  - Early Chapters of a Biography, pp 44-68, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.41)
  - Early Chapters of a Biography, pp 69-87, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.42)
  - Early Chapters of a Biography, pp 88-100, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.43)
  - Early Chapters of a Biography, pp 101-105, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.44)
  - [Early Chapters of a Biography? Notes], undated (Folder 2.45)
  - Fille de Ferme, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.46)
  - Gavin, pp 1-25, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.47)
  - Gavin, pp 26-49, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.48)
  - Histoire d’Giseaux, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.49)
  - Un Hotel Pour Animaux, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.50)
  - John Bull, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.51)
  - Lois’s Diary, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.52)
  - Nation Preconcues de la France, undated; (MS, fragment) (Folder 2.53)
  - A New Status for Overseas France, undated; (MS, fragment) (Folder 2.54)
  - A New Status for France-Overseas, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.55)
  - People Who Have Given Up Hope, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.56)
  - Un Petit Poisson, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.57)
  - Politics and Fish, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.58)
  - Portrait of a Gentleman - Last of a Line, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.59)
  - Russia: Bread, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.60)
  - Russia: The Liquidation of the "Commune", undated; (TS) (Folder 2.61)
  - Russia: Moscow: Changes, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.62)
  - Russia: Picture Book, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.63)
  - Russia: Stettin, 1921; (TS) (Folder 2.64)
  - Russia: Stettin, 1921; (TS) (Folder 2.65)
  - Russia: A Tent on the Steppe (Despair), undated; (MS) (Folder 2.66)
  - Russia: Miscellaneous Fragments, undated (Folder 2.67)
  - Saint Gonidec, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.68)
  - Les Singes d’Ivoire, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.69)
  - Souvenirs d’un Spéologue - Michel Bouillon, pp 1-30, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.70)
  - Souvenirs d’un Spéologue - Michel Bouillon, pp 31-60, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.71)
  - Souvenirs d’un Spéologue - Michel Bouillon, pp 61-89, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.72)
  - Souvenirs d’un Spéologue - Michel Bouillon, pp 90-110, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.73)
  - Souvenirs d’un Spéologue - Michel Bouillon, pp 70-90, undated; (photocopy) (Folder 2.74)
  - Souvenirs d’un Spéologue - Michel Bouillon, pp 91-110, undated; (photocopy) (Folder 2.75)
  - Summer in Brittany - Chapter I, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.76)
  - Tahiti: A-you: A Boy in Tahiti, pp 1-25, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.77)
  - Tahiti: A-you: A Boy in Tahiti, pp 26-37, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.78)
  - Tahiti: Beggarman – Thief, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.79)
  - Tahiti: The Covered Wagon: 1936, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.80)
  - Tahiti: Dead Islands, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.81)
  - Tahiti: Dead Islands The Giants Were Kinder, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.82)
  - Tahiti: The Giant Walks South, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.83)
  - Tahiti: The House on the Beach - Island Neighbors, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.84)
  - Tahiti: The House on the Beach - Chapter 2, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.85)
  - Tahiti: Land in the Pacific - The Giant Walks South, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.86)
  - Tahiti: Maison Close - Shutters?, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.87)
  - Tahiti: Music Under the Palms, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.88)
  - Tahiti: Papeete, Port of Call, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.89)
  - Tahiti: Peace in Tahiti, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.90)
  - Tahiti: Tahiti Remembered, pp 1-15, [1967]; (TS) (Folder 2.91)
  - Tahiti: Tahiti Remembered, pp 16-32, [1967]; (TS) (Folder 2.92)
  - Tahiti: Tahiti Story, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.93)
  - Tahiti: Tahiti - the Land, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.94)
  - Tahiti: Treasure Islanders, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.95)
  - Tahiti: The Tuamotus’ Big Holiday, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.96)
  - Tahiti: List of Illustrations for "The Tuamotus’ Big Holiday", undated (Folder 2.97)
  - Tahiti: What X and Mme Say About R, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.98)
  - Tahiti: Unidentified Typescript, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.99)
  - Tahiti: Miscellaneous Fragments, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.100)
  - Tahiti: Miscellaneous Fragments, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.101)
  - The Tall Men, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.102)
  - Three Sailors, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.103)
  - Time and The Siren, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.104)
  - Top Flight, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.105)
  - Top Flight, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.106)
  - Top Flight: Notebook, undated (Folder 2.107)
  - Wind, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.108)
  - Wind on the Acropolis, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.109)
  - Untitled Manuscript - Chapter 1, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.110)
  - Untitled Manuscript, undated; (MS, fragment) (Folder 2.111)
  - Untitled Manuscript, undated; (MS, fragment) (Folder 2.112)
  - Untitled Manuscript, undated; (MS, fragment) (Folder 2.113)
  - Untitled Manuscript, undated; (MS, fragment) (Folder 2.114)
  - Untitled Manuscript, undated; (TS, fragment) (Folder 2.115)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Folder 2.116)
  - Bird Shooting in the French Pyrenees, [1945] (Folder 4.4)
  - Histoire d’Giseaux, undated; (MS) (Folder 2.117)
  - Home to Brittany, undated; (TS) (Folder 4.5)
  - Nous qui Mourrons Peut-être un Jour..., pp 1-15, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.118)
  - Nous qui Mourrons Peut-être un Jour..., pp 16-30, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.119)
  - Nous qui Mourrons Peut-être un Jour..., pp 31-46, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.120)
  - Nous qui Mourrons Peut-être un Jour..., pp 47-61, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.121)
  - Nous qui Mourrons Peut-être un Jour..., pp 62-76, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.122)
  - Nous qui Mourrons Peut-être un Jour..., pp 78-90, undated; (TS) (Folder 4.6)
  - Nous qui Mourrons Peut-être un Jour..., pp 91-100, undated; (TS) (Folder 2.123)
  - Paris Gives the Tone..., undated (Folder 4.7)
  - People of France, undated (Folder 4.8)
  - The Press of Paris: 1945, undated (Folder 4.9)
  - Prise d’Armes sur les Corvettes F.N.F.L., undated (Folder 4.10)
  - Return to Paris, undated (Folder 4.11)
  - Trout Fishing in the French Pyrenees, undated (Folder 4.12)
  - Untitled Manuscript, undated; (fragment) (Folder 4.13)
- Series X. Published Manuscripts by Bergeret
  - "Christiane," The New Yorker, 1958 Nov 29; (TS) (Folder 2.124)
  - "The Pigeon Loft", undated; (TS, 19 p.) (Folder 2.125)
  - "Sailor’s Wife", undated; (TS, 20 p.) (Folder 2.126)
  - "So Tall A Lady," The New Yorker, 1960 Jul 20; (TS) (Folder 2.127)
  - The Anchored Heart, Harcourt Brace (book jacket), undated (Folder 2.128)
  - The Anchored Heart, Harcourt Brace, undated; (TS) (Box 7)
- Series XI. Published Articles by Bergeret
  - Another War Victim, The Nation, v. 118, no. 307, p. 738-39, 1924 Jun 25 (Folder 2.129)
  - Babar: The Winged Elephant, Tomorrow, p. 32-34, 1942 Sep (Folder 2.130)
  - Back to France, Tricolore: News of France at War, v. 4, no. 8, Mar.-Apr. 1945, p. 106-127, 1945 Mar-Apr (Folder 2.131)
  - Big Game, The New Yorker, p. 39-46, 1957 Oct 19 (Folder 2.132)
  - Billboard on the Rue de Longchamp, The New Yorker, 1 Mar. 1941, 1941 Mar 1 (Folder 2.133)
  - Brittany Village, Tricolore, v. 4, no. 9, p. 138-, 1945 May (Folder 2.134)
  - "Captain" Hildegard, The American Girl, p. 17-, 1930 Mar (Folder 2.135)
  - China: La Dame T’ang, The Vassar Quarterly Review, v. 34, no. 3, p. 428-438, 1958 Summer (Folder 2.136)
  - China: Interrogatoire de la Chine, Vu, p. 1-18, 1934 (Folder 2.137)
  - China: Interrogatoire de la Chine, Vu, p. 19-27, 1934 (Folder 2.138)
  - China: Interrogatoire de la Chine, Vu, p. 28-40, 1934 (Folder 2.139)
  - China: Interrogatoire de la Chine, Vu, p. 41-52, 1934 (Folder 2.140)
  - China: Interrogatoire de la Chine, Vu, p. 53-66, 1934 (Folder 2.141)
  - China’s New Zealand, The Delphian Quarterly, p. 6-12, 1942 Oct (Folder 2.142)
  - La Civilization au Secours de la Sorcellerie, Vu, no. 158, p. 403-405, undated (Folder 2.143)
  - The Clock, The New Yorker, undated (Folder 2.144)
  - Continued Story, The Nation, p. 640-642, 1941 Dec 20 (Folder 2.145)
  - Escape from Djibouti, The Saturday Evening Post, 1942 May 9 (Folder 2.146)
  - Fear Beyond Reason, The New Yorker, p. 148-, 1955 Nov 12 (Folder 2.147)
  - Fifteenth of December, The Nation, v. 136, no. 3524, p. 58-59, 1933 Jan 18 (Folder 2.148)
  - Flash Flood, Holiday, v. 42, no. 4, p. 48-, 1967 Oct (Folder 2.149)
  - France and Germany, Friends, The Nation, v.123, no. 3208, p. 688-689, 1926 Dec 29 (Folder 2.150)
  - France Comes Off the Bread Ration, Tricolore, v. 5, no. 4, p. 400+, 1945 Dec (Folder 2.151)
  - France la Deuxième Patrie, Vogue, p. 40, 80, undated (Folder 2.152)
  - A Free Frenchman Writes from the East, The Yale Review, p. 201-, including book reviews by Treat (fragment), [1941?] (Folder 2.153)
  - The French Labor Split; After the French Elections, The Nation, v. 114, no. 2973, 28 June 1922, p. 783-786; v. 118, no. 3075, 11 June 1924, p. 673-674, 1922-1924 (Folder 2.154)
  - General de Gaulle Steps Down, The Nation, p. 194-195, 1946 Feb 16 (Folder 2.155)
  - Georges Bruyere...Notre Conscience Ouvrière, unidentified publication, undated (Folder 2.156)
  - La Grotte Azilienne..., L’Anthropologie, v. 38, p. 15-, 1928 (Folder 2.157)
  - The Gun in the Corner, Tomorrow, p.15-17, undated (Folder 2.158)
  - In a French Kitchen II, Homes and Gardens, p. 49, 64, undated (Folder 2.159)
  - Insomnia and the Black Sheik, The New Yorker, 1950 Oct 21 (Folder 2.160)
  - Kassem ou la Croisiere Secrete, Vu, no. 95-97, 99-101, undated (Folder 2.161)
  - The Legion in Paris - Is This America? The Nation, v. 125, no. 3250, p. 421-422, 1927 Oct 19 (Folder 2.162)
  - The Little Family of Labo, The Vassar Quarterly Review, v.19, no. 3, p. 390-402, 1943 Summer (Folder 2.163)
  - London in the Spring, The Nation, p. 629-630, 1943 May 1 (Folder 2.164)
  - The Lorraine Cross in Scotland, Tricolore, v.4, no. 6, 1945 Jan (Folder 2.165)
  - Meeting Hitler’s Army, Harper’s Magazine, p. 472-484, undated (Folder 2.166)
  - Meeting Mr. Saito, The Nation, p. 597-599, 1942 May 23 (Folder 2.167)
  - No Obligations, The Nation, p. 256-258, 1942 Feb 28 (Folder 2.168)
  - Note sur le Permien marin de Madagascar, extract from Comptes rendus des seances de l’Academie des Sciences, vol. 182, p. 1092, 1926 May 3 (Folder 2.169)